Guide to the Jordan is Palestine, Inc. records, 1983-1995 MS2226
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jordan is Palestine, Inc. records
1921-1994
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Barrekette, Euval S. (Euval Salomon)
MS2226
1 Linear Feet
This collection contains records related to the work of the Jordan Is Palestine, Inc. The materials include correspondence, articles, articles of incorporation, bylaws, minutes, and financial records covering the dates 1983-95.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Euval Barrekette, 2007 (Accession 2007.047)
Historical or Biographical Note
The records in this collection relate to Jordan is Palestine, Inc. from New York which had as its stated goal "... to teach, and advance the historical fact that the Country called Jordan is part of mandated Palestine, and part of the territory promised to the Jewish people, as a national homeland under the Balfour Declaration and by the League of Nations;... to teach, foster, promote and educate the public at large, that Jordan is part of Palestine." David Singer founded the International Jordan is Palestine committee of which Jordan Is Palestine, Inc. was affiliated. The Jordan-is-Palestine argument holds that Palestine includes the territory on the far side of the Jordan River and therefore Jordan is the Palestinian state-even if it lacks a Palestinian ruler. Instead of two peoples fighting for one land, the Jews and the Palestinian Arabs are portrayed as controlling different territories-Jews in the western portion of Palestine, now called Israel, and Arabs in the eastern part of Palestine, now called Jordan.
The Jordan Is Palestine committee headquartered in Hyde Park, New York incorporated as Jordan Is Palestine, Inc. in 1983. In America, the two groups making the Palestine is Jordan argument to the American news media included Jordan Is Palestine, Inc. and the Washington-based CAMERA (Committee for Accuracy in Middle East Reporting in America). Jordan Is Palestine, Inc. mainly worked to reach the people it considered decision makers in the United States such as member of Congress, the White House, and opinion leaders. They promoted the use of their material by other Jewish organizations in various programs. The JIP considered itself apolitical with adherents both on the right and left regarding the Israeli-Arab conflict and did not advocate any particular solution to the Arab Israeli conflict.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, articles, bank and tax records, articles of incorporation, and meeting minutes. These record date from 1983-94. The collection has the incorporation documentation and thus may provide good background for the beginning and purpose of the organization. Most of the correspondence is between the public and JIP president H.Z. Bornstein. Some of this correspondence is with Dan Nimrod. In these letters Nimrod often discussed the JIP positions and his support or disapproval of these strategies.
This collection is not fully processed. All the material arrived loose and has been foldered into broad topics. It is available for use, but may require more additional research time to understand the order. Please contact Special Collections for more information.
Collection Organization
This collection is not processed and series have not yet been determined.
Israel; Jordan is Palestine Campaign; Zionism; New York (N.Y.); Nimrod, Dan; Jordan is Palestine Campaign; Riebenfeld, Paul S.
- Ads and circulars, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Analysis correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Corporate records: bylaws, minutes, etc., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Financial records and tax returns, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Financial records and tax returns, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Financial records and tax returns, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Financial records and tax returns, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Financial records and tax returns, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Financial records and tax returns, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Financial records: accounts, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Jordan Is Palestine Committee, 1983-1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Jordan Is Palestine Committee articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Legal documents, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letter from Dr. Paul S. Riebenfeld to Janet G. Mullins, Asst. Sect. State Department, 10/06/1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Media and government [1/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Media and government [2/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Public's mail, 1988-1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Seal, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)